Greetings, Your Highness.
太子様に拝謁を
Please get up, Madam Liu.
叔母上 お立ちください
I'd hoped you'd spend the rest of your lives in peace.
余生を安らかに過ごしてほしかったのですが
But in the end,
まさか
I still dragged you into this deadly game.
この死地へ引きずり込むことになるとは
We're at your command, Your Highness.
太子様の仰せのままに
How many people can we call on in Jiankang right now?
今 剣慷城内で動かせる者は何人いる
Twenty-seven are still alive.
生き残りは27名です
How many are under 60?
60歳以下の者は何名だ
Eleven.
11名です
But those who can still fight
ですが戦える者は
are 27.
変わらず27名おります
We're old,
廉頗は老いたりといえど
but we can still hold a sword.
まだ戦えます
Aside from us,
我々のほか
these are all the people we can mobilize
剣慷城内にはまだこれだけの者がおり
within Jiankang.
皆 我らが動かせます
We can also make use of the tunnels
地下道や
and waterways.
水路も利用できます
Tomorrow, we'll surely help Your Highness
明日 必ずや世子様をお助けし
rescue Prince Jing'an and your family.
靖安王様とご家族を救出いたします
Wuyi, don't dwell on it.
無衣 よして
You've done your utmost for Li Mao,
李茂にはもう十分仁義を尽くしたわ
yet he's the one who insists on wiping us all out.
向こうが根絶やしにしようとしてるのよ
So we don't need to suffer in silence anymore.
だからもう我慢することないわ
Once we rescue Father and Mother tomorrow
明日 父上と母君様を救い出したら
and make it out of Jiankang
剣慷を出て
to the Northern Border,
北境へ行けば
he won't be able to do anything to you.
もう李茂も手出しできなくなる
Once again, I'm dragging you into danger.
また危険な目に遭わせるな
I'm afraid things won't end well this time.
今回は無事では済まないだろう
If anything happens tomorrow,
明日 もしものことがあっても
Yaoyao,
夭夭
you must stay alive.
お前は生きろ
Remember—
いいか
no matter what happens,
何があっても
you have to stay alive.
生き延びるんだ
Don't worry.
心配しないで
Even including all of us,
私たちを合わせても
we're only a little over 30 in total.
30人余りだけど
But they all look
でも見たところ
utterly loyal and capable.
皆 忠実で頼りになりそう
Look,
考えてみて
even though you gave them free rein for over 20 years,
20年以上も放っておいたのに
they still managed to build
彼らは剣慷で
such an extensive network here.
これほどの勢力を築いたのよ
With their help tomorrow,
明日 彼らがいれば
even if we can't win in a head-on fight,
力攻めは無理でも
we should be able to
混乱を起こして
create enough chaos to rescue everyone.
人を救い出すのは問題ないわ
Yaoyao.
夭夭
I'm sorry.
すまない
Why are you apologizing?
どうして謝るの
This time, Yuanji even got punished because of us.
今回は元姫姉様まで巻き込んでしまった
But she was the top scholar of the Spring Examination—
でも元姫姉様は春月考の首席よ
the very model Li Mao uses to win over scholars throughout the realm.
李茂が学徒を味方につけるための“生きた看板”なの
Even if Li Mao is displeased that she spoke out,
上奏が不満でも
I don't think he'll truly harm her.
李茂が本気でどうこうはしないはず
Go to sleep.
もう寝よう
You...
えっ
I...
俺は
How could I possibly sleep?
眠れるわけないでしょ
Tomorrow is a battle of life and death.
明日は生死を懸けた戦いだ
This is the last peaceful night we'll ever have.
これが最後の穏やかな眠りになる
Go to sleep now.
さあ おやすみ
Mother,
母上
why were you spanked?
どうしてお尻を叩かれたの
Did you do something wrong?
何か悪いことしたの
When you grow up,
大人になったらね
you don't only get spanked for doing something wrong.
間違いを犯した時だけお尻を叩かれるんじゃないの
Sometimes, you get spanked
正しいことをしても
for doing the right thing too.
同じように叩かれるのよ
That's so unfair.
そんなのついてないや
I'd better not grow up then.
じゃあ大人になんてなりたくない
Mother,
母上
how is the plague outside?
外の疫病はどうなったの
Are Mama Ruisheng and Father
お母様と世子様のお父様は
doing well?
ご無事なの
I've finished all the lessons
母上から出されたお勉強は
Mama left for me.
全部終わらせたよ
But she still hasn't come to pick me up.
まだ迎えに来てくれない
I miss her.
会いたいな
There's a plague outside?
外では疫病がはやっている
Chan told me
嬋姉さんが言ってた
Grandfather and Grandmother had both caught it
おじい様もおばあ様も病気で
and that we had to hide in the palace to be safe.
皇宮にいないと危ないって
Have they recovered yet?
お二人の病はもう治ったの
A plague doesn't end that quickly.
疫病がそんなにすぐ終わるものか
Young Master Xiao, please rest easy in the palace.
蕭様 どうか宮中でご安心を
Tomorrow, your father
明日には世子の父上が
will come into the palace to be with you.
宮中に参られおそばにおられます
What about my mama, Ruisheng?
母上は
Your mama is a physician.
母上は医者だから
There are so many sick people outside.
外は病人が大勢いるの
She has to treat them, right?
皆を診てあげないと そうでしょう
Young Master Xiao, take good care of your mother.
蕭様 母上をしっかりお支えなさい
I'm sure your family will be reunited soon.
すぐに一家で暮らせます
These are the sugar cakes His Highness made especially for you.
これは殿下がそなたのために作った飴菓子です
So this is how you've been fooling him.
そうやってあの子を言いくるめたのね
His Highness said
殿下のお言葉です
grown-up matters
大人の事情を
aren't something a child needs to know.
子供に知らせる必要はないと
You just said
先ほど言ったわね
Young Lord Xiao would enter the palace tomorrow.
世子が明日入宮すると
What does that mean?
どういうこと
We heard Young Lord Xiao has already entered the city.
世子はすでに入城されたとか
His Highness fears he may have caught the plague outside
殿下は世子が外で病に感染したのではとご心配で
and plans to invite him and the others to the palace tomorrow
明日 宮中にお招きし
to visit Prince Jing'an and the Princess.
王爺と王妃にお目通りを、と
Is Xiao Yao sick too?
蕭堯も病に
Is he dying as well?
死ぬほど重いのですか
Lady He,
何様
it hasn't been easy for you to get where you are today.
これまで苦労なされたでしょう
His Highness has given you a place to prove yourself.
殿下は居場所を与えてくださった
Don't throw away his goodwill for the sake of people
無関係な者のために
who have nothing to do with you.
殿下のご厚意を無になさいませんよう
Attend to them carefully.
よくお仕えしろ
Don't let Lady He and Young Master Xiao
何様と蕭様を
come into contact with anyone from outside and catch the plague.
部外者に会わせ 病に感染させるな
Yes.
はっ
The execution ground is ready?
刑場の準備は整いました
Good.
よし
Tomorrow, I'll let the whole world see
では明日 世間に見せてやろう
just what kind of loyal subject Xiao Wuyi really is.
蕭無衣がいかなる忠臣であるかを
Three,
三
two,
二
one.
一
Go save them!
助けろ
That's the execution drum.
刑場の太鼓だ
We've been tricked by Li Mao!
李茂にだまされた
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
There's no time. Go save them quickly.
時間がない 早く助けに行け
Leave this to us.
ここは我々に任せろ
Qing Long, protect Jiayu.
青龍 嘉魚を守れ
Yes.
はっ
Be careful.
気をつけろ
Madam Liu, let's go.
柳女官 行くぞ
Stand aside.
どけ
If Your Highness repents,
世子が過ちに気づき引き返すなら
you may yet have a chance to survive.
まだ助かる道もありましょう
Kill him!
殺せ
You're all citizens of Ye.
そなたたちは皆 大鄴の民だ
I don't want to see your blood spilled.
そなたたちの血は見たくない
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣よ
is this what you call
目の前のこの光景が
serving the nation with all your heart?
そなたの言う国を思う心か
Prince Jing'an Xiao Ju framed loyal officials
靖安王 蕭駒は忠臣を陥れ
and fabricated a miscarriage of justice,
冤罪を作り
endangering the fate of the nation and leading to the fall of the Capital.
大鄴の国運を危うくし 上京を陥落させた
His intent violates the law,
その心は裁かれ
and his crimes warrant execution.
その罪は誅されるべきである
Yet today, in broad daylight,
しかし白日の下に
you slaughter the Imperial Guards
禁軍を殺し
and storm the execution ground.
刑場を襲うとは
Where does that leave the law of the land?
国法をいずこに置き
Where does that leave justice for the realm?
天下の公理をいずこに置くつもりか
Heaven's principles are clear,
天理は明白であり
and the law of the land cannot tolerate this.
国法は許さぬ
If the entire Jing'an household is not brought to justice today,
今日 靖安王府の者どもを法に伏させねば
how can I answer to the realm?
どうやって天下を従わせる
And how can I uphold the order of the state?
どうやって国綱を正すのか
Li Mao!
李茂
I've already given you
お前の望むものは
everything you wanted.
すべて与えた
Except for one thing.
まだ一つ足りない
What exactly do you want?
一体 何が望みだ
A just cause.
大義名分だ
I'm giving you one last chance.
最後の機会をやる
Let my family go.
私の家族を解放しろ
I am the Regent of the realm.
私は今の監国だ
Are you trying to rebel?
謀反でも起こす気か
His Majesty's imperial edict!
陛下の勅令である
I rule all under heaven and uphold
朕は万物を統べ
the virtue of wise governance.
その明徳を示す
The truth of the An-Lu wrongful case has been revealed.
安陸の冤罪の真相は明白となった
Prince Jing'an Xiao Ju
靖安王 蕭駒は
harbored malicious intentions and framed loyal subjects.
よからぬことを企み 忠臣を陥れた
Today, the Xiao family has been brought to justice.
本日 蕭氏一門は皆 法に伏した
I hereby order Xiao Wuyi to surrender and confess immediately.
蕭無衣に特命を下す 即刻武装を解き罪を認めよ
Do not disappoint me,
朕の信頼を損なうな
and do not let the people of the realm suffer further from the war.
天下の民を再び戦乱に巻き込むことなかれ
Beifu Black Cavalry,
北府黒騎
seize the criminal Xiao Wuyi at once.
早く罪人 蕭無衣を捕らえぬか
Do you really think my Beifu soldiers
本気で私の北府兵が
will take orders from you?
お前に従うとでも
Then let's find out.
ならば試すがいい
Seize the criminal!
罪人を捕らえよ
Isn't this moment ironic?
実に皮肉なものだな
You once poured your heart and soul
かつてお前は心血を注ぎ
into pushing through the Beifu Reform,
北府の改制を進めた
even going so far as to turn the private army loyal to you and your clan
一族の私兵を
into an army for the nation.
天下の兵とすることさえ いとわなかった
What courage.
その気概
What vision.
その度量
But I doubt you ever imagined
だが まさか思うまい
that the very army you built with such devotion
お前が心血を注いだ北府軍に
would one day
いつの日か
turn on you
刃を向けられ
and take your life.
返り討ちに遭うとはな
Mao, you...
茂… お前
Execute!
斬れ
Brother!
兄上
Let my family go.
家族を放せ
Let go of me!
放せ
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Give Yaoyao back to me...
夭夭を返せ
Let go!
放せ
Li Mao, you lunatic!
李茂 この狂人が
Tell them to let go of me!
私を放させろ
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Li Mao!
李茂
Li Mao, you're crazy!
李茂 狂ったのか
Let go of me!
手を放せ
Xiao Wuyi,
蕭無衣
with this arrow,
この矢で
we're even!
借りは返した
Li Mao, you're crazy!
李茂 狂っている
Kill them!
殺せ
Don't kill my father.
父上を殺さないで
Execute!
斬れ
No!
やめて
Father...
父上
Mother...
母上
Li Mao.
李茂
I will make you pay for this.
絶対に許さない
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Yaoyao...
夭夭
Capture the traitor
逆臣を捕らえよ
and kill the rebels!
賊を討て
Qing Long, Yan Yue, protect the Heir!
青龍 偃月 世子様をお守りしろ
Kill them!
殺せ
Bring Xie Jiayu back to the palace.
謝嘉魚を宮中に連れ帰れ
Your Highness!
世子様
Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣
Your Highness, we're safe now.
世子様 もう安全です
Where should we go?
どこへ向かえば
Let's go back to the Northern Border.
北境へ戻れ
There's mist. Be careful.
霧だ 気をつけろ
Yan Yue!
偃月
You haven't eaten in days.
もう何日も食しておらぬだろう
Whatever you want to say,
言いたいことがあるなら
say it after you've eaten.
食事が済んでからだ
Yaoyao,
夭夭
you once told me that
以前 そなたは言った
even if Xiao Wuyi died before you,
蕭無衣が先に逝こうと
as long as he had never betrayed you
彼が裏切らず
or let you down,
失望もさせなければ
you would still carry on living for him.
彼の分まで生きると
Come on, eat.
早く食べろ
Are you going to keep me here forever?
私を一生監禁する気？
You should know what I'm capable of.
私の腕はご存じのはず
No lock in this world
この世のいかなる錠も
can hold me.
私を閉じ込めてはおけないわ
Locks can't hold you,
錠では無理でも
but poison can.
毒を使えばよい
Muscle-Weakening Powder.
軟筋散だ
At least it'll make sure you can't go anywhere,
これなら お前はどこへも行けぬ
so we can get married in peace.
大人しく私と祝言を挙げるのだな
You might as well kill me now!
それならいっそ 今殺して
Otherwise, as long as I'm alive,
でなければ 私が生きている限り
I'll avenge Xiao Wuyi!
蕭無衣の敵を討つわ
You already stabbed me with a hairpin once.
かんざしで一度刺しただろう
Xiao Wuyi isn't dead.
蕭無衣は死んでいない
He escaped the city.
城の外へ逃げた
When he fled,
逃げた時は
he was heavily injured.
重傷だった
I'd already laid an ambush outside the city.
余はとっくに城外に伏兵を置いたが
Yet the moment he got out,
城を出た途端
someone rescued him.
何者かに助けられたようだ
Tell me,
申せ
who saved him?
一体 何者だ
Does he still have hidden private troops?
私兵を隠しているのか
Looks like you don't know either.
そなたも知らぬようだな
Xie Jiayu,
謝嘉魚
it seems he never truly trusted you.
彼もそなたを信用してはいないらしい
Bad news, Your Highness!
大変です 殿下
Insolent!
無礼者
How dare you barge in without announcing yourself?
誰の許しで断りなく入った
Forgive me, Your Highness.
殿下 お許しを
I have an urgent matter to report.
急ぎの報告がございます
Speak.
申せ
Xiao... Xiao Ziqi is missing.
しょ… 蕭子期が消えました
After knocking out Miss Chan with acupuncture,
鍼で阿嬋さんを気絶させ
he ran away.
逃げたとのこと
He is nowhere to be found now.
今は行方が分かりません
Search the palace and find him now!
直ちに宮中を捜索し 奴を捜し出せ
Yes.
はっ
When you see Grand Tutor Xie later,
後で太傅に会っても
don't cry.
泣くんじゃない
Death wipes the slate clean.
死んだ者の過ちは水に流し
Don't hold a grudge against him anymore.
恨むのはよせ
Execute!
斬れ
Brother!
兄上
Xiao Ziqi is missing.
蕭子期が消えました
Search the palace and find him now!
直ちに宮中を捜索し 奴を捜し出せ
In my first year in the palace,
入宮した最初の年
I, too, often stood here alone, deep in thought.
私もここで一人 よく物思いにふけっていた
I'd wonder
何を
what you and Wuyi were doing
そなたと無衣が宮殿の外で
outside the palace.
何をしているだろうかと
At first, I imagined
最初はこう考えていた
you were probably blowing up
そなたは家で
the alchemy furnace again at home,
また練丹炉を壊しただろうと
while Wuyi might be off at the Northern Border,
無衣は北境で
where swords clash and battles rage.
修羅場をくぐっているかと
But the longer I thought about it,
だが考えれば考えるほど
the fewer images of you I could conjure.
そなたたちの面影は薄れていった
Until one day,
そしてある日
I couldn't picture you at all anymore.
もうそなたたちの顔さえ思い出せなくなった
Years later,
数年後
I came back here again to think.
私はまたここで考えていた
I wondered
その時 考えていたのは
what we would have done together
もし あの時そなたが宮中に残っておれば
if you had stayed in the palace back then.
そなたと共に何をしたいだろうかと
I thought about it for a long,
長いこと考えた
long time.
長いこと考えていた
But I couldn't come up with a single scenario
でも あなたが喜び 私も喜ぶ
where you'd be happy, and I'd be happy too.
そんな光景は思い浮かばなかった
Yet just now, I understood.
でも さっき分かった
Just having you stand quietly by my side...
こうして静かにそばにいてくれる
is enough.
それだけで十分
Now my wish has been fulfilled.
もう願いはかなったわ
There are
私たちの間に
no more regrets left between us.
もう何の悔いもない
You seem very worried about Ziqi.
子期のことがご心配なのですね
Why would you, Prince Qi,
蕭無衣を
who drove Xiao Wuyi into a corner,
窮地に追い詰めた岐王殿下が
care so much
なぜ取るに足らぬ
about an insignificant child?
子供を心配なさるのです
Are you hiding something from me?
何か隠し事をなさってませんか
We've found him!
見つかりました
Your Highness,
殿下
Eunuch Feng has found Young Master Xiao.
馮公公が蕭公子をお見つけになりました
Give me your hands.
手を
Aren't you afraid I'll run away too?
私が逃げるとは思わないの
If you were to run,
逃げるとしても
you'd surely find Xiao Ziqi first.
蕭子期を見つけてからでしょう
Let's go.
行くわよ
Little master.
若君
Little master, please stop.
若君 おやめください
Come on, let's go.
さあ 行きましょう
Stop playing.
ふざけるのはおよしなさい
Let go of me!
離せ
I want to find my mama!
母上を探す
You're all liars!
うそつき
Alright, alright.
よしよし
There is no plague outside at all!
外に疫病などない
Auntie, help!
叔母上 助けて
They're all bad people!
こいつらは悪者だ
They beat Mother!
母上が叩かれて
-Mama is missing. -Young Master Xiao.
いなくなったんだ
They're all bad people!
こいつらは悪者だ
Bad people! You big villain!
悪党 この大悪党
You killed my grandfather and grandmother!
祖父上と祖母上を殺し
-Alright. -You even want to kill my father too!
世子である父上まで殺そうとしてる
Feng An,
馮安
take him back to the Eastern Palace.
東宮へ連れていけ
If he escapes again,
二度と逃がすな
you'll answer for it yourself.
さもなくば罰する
Yes, Your Highness.
御意
Let's go. Come on.
行くぞ
Hurry.
早くしろ
Stay put.
動くな
Da,
阿大
next time you want me to stay put,
次に私を制する時は
just use this hand signal.
この合図にしてくれ
Right.
そう
Xiao Wuyi isn't dead.
蕭無衣は死んでいない
He escaped the city.
城外へ逃げたのよ
Mao,
阿茂
that letter you didn't get a chance to give me
私に渡せなかった文は
is from Wuyi, right?
無衣からでしょう
Give it to me.
それをちょうだい
How did you know?
なぜお分かりに
From the way you treated Ziqi.
子期への態度です
How could someone who slaughtered innocent people
刑場で無実の人を殺める方が
at the execution ground be so concerned about a child?
なぜ子供１人をあれほどご心配に
Unless
もしや…
it's all an act.
全てが偽りなのでは
So I went back over everything that's happened
それでこの数日の出来事を
these past few days,
改めて考え直しました
along with the hand signal Da just gave me.
先ほどの阿大の合図と
And these medicinal herbs.
この薬草を合わせ
I was already 90% certain.
９割方 推測できました
These precious herbs
この高価な薬草は
are all used to treat blood stasis.
すべて血瘀を治すものです
If you truly meant to kill Wuyi,
本当に無衣を殺す気なら
why would you have someone brew medicine for him here?
薬を作らせたりしません
What about the other 10%?
では残りの１割は
I was bluffing.
カマをかけたのです
How do you recognize these herbs?
なぜこの薬草が分かった
I taught her.
私が世子妃にお教えしました
Prince Qi sought out the miraculous doctor
岐王殿下が神医を捜し出され
to treat the Heir.
世子様を治療しています
You knew all along too?
とっくに知っていたのね
Then how is Xiao Wuyi now...
では蕭無衣は今…
As long as that arrow struck exactly where it was meant to,
あの矢が狙いどおりの場所に刺さっていれば
his life is not in danger.
命に別状はない
As for the blood stasis,
血瘀については
the miraculous doctor has prepared pills.
神医が丸薬を処方した
They can at least keep the Heir stable
少なくとも世子様は
for 2 months.
２か月は安泰だ
Da's men are all trustworthy.
阿大が連れてきた者たちは信用できる
Give it to me.
渡して
"My dear wife Jiayu,
我が妻 嘉魚へ
I hope this letter finds you well.
息災か
I told Yizhi that once he confirmed
易之には 私が北秦の密偵に
I'd been captured by Northern Qin spies,
捕らわれたと確信したら
he should tell you the whole truth
そなたに真相をすべて話すよう伝えてある
to spare you prolonged fear and grief.
長く案じさせぬために
But you must have already cried by now.
だが そなたはもう泣いてしまっただろう
The thought of this
そう思うと
unsettles my heart.
胸が痛む
Yaoyao,
夭夭
I, Xiao Wuyi, have never failed anyone in my life,
この蕭無衣は生涯 誰をも裏切らなかった
except you.
そなたただ一人を除いては
Perhaps this will be my final letter in this lifetime.
これが最後の手紙になるやもしれぬ
Even so, I still want to start from where it all began: Crown Prince Wenxi.
まずは文熹太子のことから話そう
Before I turned 13,
13歳になるまで
I believed my fate would be the same as Father's
私の運命は父王や
and all my uncles'—
叔父上たちと同じだと思っていた
to become a commander of the Imperial Guards,
禁軍統領として
protecting the palace and the imperial throne.
宮城と皇権を守るのだと
But then Northern Qin invaded Qizhou.
だが北秦が岐州に侵攻し
That was the first time I saw a real battlefield.
初めて本物の戦場を目の当たりにした
It was also the first time I learned of my true identity.
そして初めて己の出自を知った
One hundred and forty-seven
私の命を守るため
Shadow Envoys sacrificed their lives to save me.
147人もの影使が命を落とした
From now on, your name is Xiao Sheng.
これからお前は蕭晟と名乗れ
From today on, he is your master.
今後 この方がお前たちのご主人様だ
Greetings, Your Highness.
世子様
He's Qing Long.
こちらは青龍
She's Yan Yue.
こちらは偃月
From now on, they will remain by your side.
今後は世子様に従え
"I held the Phoenix Heart Token,
雀骨令を手にし
and the expectation that 'when the Phoenix Heart Token appears,
「雀骨出でて 天下定まる」との期待を背負うも
Yet in my heart, I felt utterly lost.
心はひどく途方に暮れていた
If the infamous An-Lu treason case
もし あの
that shook the entire realm
大鄴を揺るがした安陸の謀反事件が
were truly a miscarriage of justice,
冤罪であり
and my parents were the root cause
我が両親こそ上京を陥落させ
of the Capital's fall and 20 years of war,
20年の戦乱を招いた元凶だとしたら
could I really, with just a single token,
令牌一つで
command all under heaven
人々を動かし
and bring peace to the realm?
天下を平定できるのか
Are the elite troops of Ye meant only to fight for the powerful and noble...
大鄴の精兵は権力者のためだけに戦い
It was only after I met Yizhi...
易之と出会い
Not for the common people?
民のために戦わぬのか
That I found my direction.
ようやく道が見えたのだ
It wasn't wrong for Emperor Wenxi and the Empress
文熹帝后が寒門を登用し
to support commoner officials in order to check the noble clans.
豪族や名家を抑えたのは間違いではない
They simply chose the wrong time
ただ 時機を誤り
and failed to keep the right balance.
度を越したことで
That gave Northern Qin the opening it needed.
北秦につけ入る隙を与えた
Then what, in your view, is the right time,
では好機とはいつだと
and how should that balance be kept?
そのさじ加減は
The past is the past,
当時は当時
and now is now.
今は今です
We are now in a chaotic age,
今はすでに乱世
and a chaotic age calls for harsh laws.
乱世には厳罰が必須です
Thank you. Your words
そなたの言葉に感謝する
have enlightened me.
この兄の迷いは晴れた
Ye needs an army
大鄴には
that truly fights for the people and the nation.
民と国のために戦う真の軍隊が必要だ
Compared to Jiankang Palace,
剣慷宮よりも
I belonged more on the Northern Border.
私は北境へ行くべきだ
Eight years of war
８年にわたる戦いの末
gave Ye the Beifu Army,
大鄴に北府軍が生まれた
and Xiao Sheng became Xiao Wuyi.
蕭晟は蕭無衣となった
Yizhi was right.
易之の言うとおりだ
If I hadn't been gravely wounded at Jiuzhang Plain,
九丈原での重傷がなければ
perhaps I might eventually have
蕭無衣もいつかは
become Crown Prince Wenxi.
文熹太子になるだろう
But my blood stasis disease dooms me to a short life.
だが血瘀の病では長生きは望めぬ
Grand Tutor Xie's selfish desires
謝太傅の私心が
also showed me another, better path.
より良い別の道を示してくれた
Yizhi is more suited for that throne.
この地位には易之の方がふさわしい
The mistakes my father made in the past
父上が過去に犯した過ちは
have always been a hidden danger to the army's morale.
軍の士気を揺るがす火種となる
I had prepared for that long ago.
それは覚悟の上だったが
But I didn't expect the Eagle King to use the Grand Tutor's life as bait.
鷹王が太傅の命を餌にするとは
Since he made his move,
彼が動いたなら
we might as well uproot the old grievances once and for all.
我々も過去を根こそぎ清算する
So we turned his scheme against him
相手の策に乗じて
and staged a fallout between the ruler and his subject—
君臣の決裂を演じるのだ
paving the way with flesh and blood.
この身をもって道を開く
Take this secret report
この密書を
and read it carefully.
よく読むがいい
Beware of spies.
密偵に気をつけろ
I planned everything
私は全てを計画し
and arranged it all.
手はずを整えた
To achieve the final goal,
最終目的のためなら
I can sacrifice anything.
どんな犠牲もいとわない
But the only exception
だが唯一の例外
is you.
それはお前だ
I was afraid that if I told you,
お前に話せば
I'd lose the courage to walk this path alone.
独りで進む勇気を失いそうで怖かった
But with the fate of the realm on my shoulders,
だが国の重責を背負う
I couldn't afford to cling to my own life."
無衣はこの身を惜しむことなどできぬ
Xiao Wuyi, you're a liar!
蕭無衣 あんたは嘘つきだ
Bastard!
この野郎
Jerk!
馬鹿野郎
Why didn't you tell me?
なぜ言わなかったの
When did you two bastards
二人ともろくでなし
conspire to send him
いったいいつから彼を死地に送る
to his death?
相談をしていたの
And that arrow—
それにあの矢は
whose idea was that really?
いったい誰の差し金なの
That night in the imperial prison,
詔獄でのあの夜
when you left,
二人が去った時
the stab he gave me
彼が私を斬ったのは
was for Feng An to see.
馮安に見せるためだった
The next time we meet,
次に会えば
there's no need to hold back.
容赦は無用
No!
やめて
-Xiao Wuyi! -Kill them!
蕭無衣 殺せ
So,
つまり
you told Da to stay put
阿大に兵を動かさぬよう命じたのは
because, aside from the Northern Qin spies
剣慷宮にいる
who had already been exposed outside Jiankang Palace,
発見済みの北秦の密偵より
the one you were really guarding against was Eunuch Feng?
真に警戒すべきが馮公公だったからね
Not just guarding against him—
警戒するだけでなく
you were using him.
利用するためだった
You wanted to use his words
彼の口を使って
to make the Eagle King believe
鷹王に信じ込ませるため
that even if you knew something was wrong with the case,
事件に裏があると分かっていても
you would still suspect Xiao Wuyi
蕭無衣を疑い
and force him into a corner?
彼を窮地に追い込むしかなかった
At least we had him.
せめて彼が
What did the miraculous doctor mean by 2 months?
神医が言っていた２か月とはどういう意味
He's suffered from blood stasis
彼はもとより血瘀の持病があり
and taken an arrow.
矢を受け
After that long, rough journey back to the Northern Border,
北境まで揺られて行った
things won't go well for him.
穏やかに過ごせるはずもない
But the miraculous doctor's medicine
でも神医の薬では
can only keep him alive for 2 months.
２か月しか命を保てない
Did it ever occur to you
考えなかったの
that he might not return within 2 months?
２か月以内に彼が戻れなかったらどうするの
What if the Eagle King doesn't
もし鷹王があなたたちを信じず
fall for your plan and refuses to take the bait?
掘った穴に落ちなかったらどうするの
Yaoyao.
夭夭
Don't be mad anymore.
怒らないでくれ
I'm not mad.
怒ってないわ
I'm just thinking about
ただ考えてたの
how I'm going to bury this bastard.
あのろくでなしの亡骸をどう始末しようかと
I have something for you.
渡したいものがある
This was made
これだ
by melting down the Phoenix Heart Token
蕭無衣が砕いた雀骨令を
that Xiao Wuyi cut in half.
溶かして作ったものだ
He wanted me to give it to you.
お前に渡してくれと
This was originally my mother's Phoenix Imperial Seal.
これは元々母后の鳳印だ
How about I melt it
いっそ溶かして作り直し
and make it into a hairpin for you?
そなたのかんざしにするのはどうだ
Both Her Highness and I
私も郡主様も
wish for you to live freely and happily.
そなたが自由に楽しく生きることを願っている
"The road ahead is long,
この道は遠く
and I may never return.
帰る日はないだろう
This is my farewell to you.
そなたと訣別し
I have failed you.
その心に背く
I dare not ask for another life together.
来世など望めぬ
I only wish that in this life, Yaoyao, you may meet a good man again
夭夭が今生で良き人と巡り会い
♪ I fear you might have forgotten me ♪
平安に暮らせるように
Is His Highness the Eagle King still not coming out to receive the imperial edict?
鷹王殿下は まだ勅命を受けにおいでにならないのですか
Your Excellency,
勅使様
His Highness is ill
我が殿下はご病気で
and cannot come out to receive the edict for the time being.
しばらく勅命はお受けできませぬ
Preposterous!
馬鹿な
Since when does receiving an edict depend on one's convenience?
勅命を伝えるのに時を選ぶとは
The Eagle King should not presume that being the Emperor's uncle
鷹王は陛下の叔父であることを笠に着て
exempts him from observing the proper hierarchy.
上下のわきまえもお忘れか
We wouldn't dare.
滅相もございません
His Highness has always
我が殿下は陛下に対し
held His Majesty in the highest respect.
常に敬意を払っております
Isn't that right, everyone?
お前たち そうだよな
Yes!
はっ
His Majesty has heard
陛下のお耳に入っております
that the Eagle King brought back an honored guest from Southern Ye.
鷹王が南鄴より貴人を招き入れたと
His Majesty wishes to invite this honored guest to visit the Capital.
陛下はその貴人を上京へお招きになりたいとのこと
Here is the imperial edict.
勅命はこれに
If His Highness the Eagle King
もし鷹王殿下が
still refuses to come out to receive the edict,
それでもお出ましにならぬのであれば
then I
では このわしが
will have to proclaim it here.
ここで読み上げるまで
Wait, wait.
お待ちを
My stomach...
腹が…
Take me to the latrine.
早く厠へ
Escort the Imperial Envoy to the guest residence.
勅使様を別館へお連れしろ
Young Lord Xiao,
世子殿
what do you suppose my dear nephew, the Emperor,
我が甥の皇帝が
wants with you in the Capital?
そなたを上京に呼んだ理由が分かるか
You're really no fun, you know?
そうつれない態度はつまらんな
You and I have fought for a decade.
そなたと俺は10年も戦ってきた
How many decades does a man get in one lifetime?
人生で10年はそう何度もない
That makes us friends of a sort, doesn't it?
もはや戦友であろう
Now that you're on my turf,
我が領地に来ておきながら
you don't even let me
この王に
play the gracious host
もてなしもさせず
and treat you to a good meal.
肉も食わぬとは
You're refusing even water on your hunger strike.
水一滴すら飲まぬとは
It makes me look like a terribly ill-mannered host.
俺が礼儀知らずに見えるではないか
Fine.
分かった
If you won't talk,
そなたが話さぬなら
I'll go have a chat with that guard of yours instead.
そちらの護衛と話すとしよう
Her injuries look even worse than yours.
そなたより重傷のようだが
Maybe her temper isn't quite as foul.
気性はそなたほどひねくれてはまい
Don't waste your breath on me.
私に構っても無駄骨だ
Returning to Jiankang was a gamble
剣慷に戻ったのは
I chose to take.
賭けだったからだ
And now that I've lost,
賭けに負けた以上
unlike you,
そなたとは違う
I accept whatever comes—life or death.
生死は甘んじて受け入れよう
Unlike me?
俺とは違うだと？
At the Battle of Jiuzhang Plain,
九丈原の戦で
your Black Eagle Army suffered heavy losses,
黒鷹軍は壊滅的な被害を受けた
and your Empress Dowager passed away shortly after.
その後 北秦の太后が病死
Your biggest support is gone.
そなたは最大の盾を失った
The new Emperor has ascended the throne.
新帝が即位し
You refuse to resign yourself to that and urgently need a great victory.
不満を抱くそなたは 大勝利を切望している
But your young Emperor doesn't want you to win.
だが 若き皇帝はそなたの勝利を望んでいない
That's why he demands you hand me over,
だから私を奪いに来た
afraid that you and I might join forces.
そなたと私が組むのを恐れてな
But have you ever thought about this?
だが 考えたことはあるか
The fact that he moved so quickly
なぜ若き皇帝がこうも早く私を奪いに来れたのか
means your own ranks
つまり そなたの周りも
aren't exactly airtight.
一枚岩ではないということだ
Sure enough,
やはり
the one who knows you best is not your friend,
己を最も知る者は 友ではなく
but your enemy.
敵だということか
Yet aren't you even more foolish than I am?
だが俺以上に愚かだな
Li Mao used you
あの李茂はそなたを利用し
to secure his throne,
朝廷での地位を固めた
then the moment he had the chance, he turned on you—
そして好機と見るや すぐさま梯子を外したのだ
killed your family and took your wife.
そなたの父兄を殺し 妻を奪った
How much longer
そのような主君に
are you going to tolerate a ruler like that?
まだ我慢がなるのか
Why not
いっそ
join forces with me?
私と手を組まぬか
Tell me the Beifu Army's defense strategies.
そなたが北府軍の防衛戦略を教えれば
From Luozhou to Huaixi,
洛州から淮西まで
it'll all be
瞬く間に
within our grasp in an instant.
我々のものとなろう
We'll divide the realm between us.
天下を分かち合おうではないか
My loyalty is to the nation—
私が忠誠を誓うは国であり
not to any one ruler.
一人の君主ではない
Then what if I promise to help you fight your way back into Jiankang
ならば余が剣慷の奪還を手伝い
and snatch Xie Jiayu back?
謝嘉魚を取り戻すと言えばどうだ
Then you can personally cut off Li Mao's head
さらに李茂の首をはね
and offer it in tribute to your family. How about that?
そなたの父兄を弔ってやるというのは
My days are already numbered.
私の命はもう長くない
Wealth and glory,
栄華富貴も
love and desire,
男女の情も
mean nothing to me.
私には何の意味もない
Who would've thought
まさか
that the illustrious Crown Prince Wenxi
堂々たる文熹太子が
would turn out to be such a waste— handing the realm over to someone else.
国を譲り渡すような腑抜けだったとはな
H-How did you know that?
な… なぜそれを
If I didn't even know that,
余がこれしきも知らずに
how could I dare play a game of divide and conquer?
離間の計など仕掛けられようか
You planted Li Lejun
そなたらは余のもとへ
by my side.
李楽君を送り込んだが
Did you really think I had no one planted in your Eastern Palace?
東宮に余の人間がいないとでも思ったか
Let me tell you.
言っておくが
Li Mao is narrow-minded, indecisive, and vicious by nature.
李茂は偏狭で優柔不断かつ陰険だ
Precisely because you're Crown Prince Wenxi,
そなたが文熹太子だからこそ
he will never truly trust you,
李茂は決して信用せぬ
let alone let you command the Beifu Army.
北府の指揮を任せるはずもない
Even if you help him retake the Capital,
仮に上京を奪還したとて
you will end up being discarded when you outlive your usefulness.
待つのは兎死狗烹の末路のみ
Look closely.
よく見よ
This is the armor Emperor Wenxi wore when he fell in battle.
これは文熹帝が戦死される前に身に着けていた鎧だ
Back then, he personally led the campaign,
かつて帝は自ら出陣し
holding off overwhelming enemy forces.
大軍に立ち向かわれた
But to his dying breath, he never saw the reinforcements
だが死ぬまでついに
from your Southern Ye noble clans.
南鄴の名家からの援軍は来なかった
Is such a realm
そのような南鄴に
still worth protecting?
守る価値などあるのか
Oh,
そうだ
and the day after you left Jiankang,
そなたが剣慷を離れた翌日
Li Mao issued a decree:
李茂は勅旨を下した
the Xiao family committed treason,
蕭氏の謀反を理由に
you were reduced to a commoner,
そなたを庶人に落とすと
and every member of the Xiao family aged 14 and above was beheaded.
蕭氏の14歳以上は全員斬首
On the third day,
三日後
another decree came from the palace
宮中より勅旨が下り
that Xie Jiayu was to be taken as his secondary consort.
謝嘉魚を岐王の側妃に迎えるとされた
Xie resisted to the point of threatening her own life,
謝氏は死をもって抗ったが
so he had her shackled inside the Eastern Palace.
岐王に足かせをはめられ東宮に囚われている
The wedding will be held tomorrow.
婚儀は明日だ